<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Glassbeans - Personal views on how machine learning and AI will help us see through business</title>
    <link>http://www.glassbeans.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Glassbeans - Personal views on how machine learning and AI will help us see through business</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.glassbeans.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Google&#39;s Pictionary Technology to Find Risky Customers</title>
      <link>http://www.glassbeans.com/blog/pictionary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.glassbeans.com/blog/pictionary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does anyone still play Pictionary? The guessing game where someone on your team draws a picture, and you have to guess what it is. I was an okay Pictionary player. I think I was a better ‘guesser’ than a ‘drawer.’ I could draw inanimate objects well enough, but if I was ever asked to draw something more complicated like a cat or giraffe, things get ugly. Anyone remember that old episode of The Simpsons where Millhouse’s dad tried drawing “dignity”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google this week released a game called Quick, Draw! where you, the drawer, is given an object that you need to draw and Google’s AI will try to guess what it is. Here’s what happened when I attempted a truck:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.glassbeans.com/img/main/Truck doodle.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I draw like a five-year-old. For those that are interested, you can play the game &lt;a href=&#34;https://quickdraw.withgoogle.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have drawn the truck a million ways. It could have been drawn from a different angle, with varying level of details, and with various proportions since I’m sketching this with a desktop mouse. Despite these variations, Google’s technology was able to recognize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why am I talking about an online Google sketch game?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this week I was asked by one of our clients about what data analytics could do for their business. The business is an online brokerage, and the people I was speaking to were in the compliance department. One of their key responsibilities is to assess customer risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk is one of those areas where predictive analytics has a great use case because it is highly subjective and is dependent on professional judgment. Compliance departments usually already have ways they assess customer risk. Most commonly, risk is determined using a combination of thresholds and criteria filters. For example, if a customer worked in what our client deemed as a high-risk occupation, the compliance department might want to flag that customer as high-risk. These criteria and thresholds can be quite costly and time-consuming to set up because it takes time for a knowledgeable professional to think through all the possible scenarios that don’t add up and then write a rule for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if this business looks through their customer database and sees an elementary school teacher depositing $5,000 every week, maybe they would think it’s a little unusual. Maybe they would want their system to screen that person. But if you start thinking about all the different scenarios that could be considered unusual, the complexity and sheer quantity of the rules you’d need to write would get very messy very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to my doodle of a truck. How do you think Google recognized my drawing? Maybe they hired an army of interns to go through a dictionary and program in complex rules for every object? “Hey Billy, welcome to Google, today we’re going to have you write down every conceivable way someone could draw a truck. After that, we’re going to move you to cars. If you do a great job, we’ll get you to vans as well”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, it doesn’t quite work that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go back and look my truck doodle, you’ll see that the results page says “You drew this, and the neural net recognized it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.glassbeans.com/img/main/Results.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A neural net is a technique used to “learn” outcomes if you can give it enough examples. Feed neural nets enough drawings of trucks, and over time it will recognize that it’s a truck rather than a car or a turtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to risk, if we can feed a model enough “drawings” of risky customers, over time we can get a very accurate prediction of which new customers are considered high-risk. The implication of this is we can get a more precise assessment of customer risk, thereby lowering the risk for the overall organization. More than that, we will also be able to reduce the time needed to scrutinize customers classified as high-risk that shouldn’t have been classified that way in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still hurdles that we will need to overcome, including regulatory restrictions and the transparency of using advanced algorithms. However, as the utilization of these technologies becomes increasingly widespread, I believe we will begin to see more and more organizations adopt these methods as their preferred risk assessment approach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Centaurs will dominate the future</title>
      <link>http://www.glassbeans.com/blog/why-centaurs-will-dominate-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.glassbeans.com/blog/why-centaurs-will-dominate-the-future/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-machine-learning-and-ai-is-shaping-the-needs-of-tomorrow&#34;&gt;How machine learning and AI is shaping the needs of tomorrow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+++&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the day when IBM’s Deep Blue defeated Gary Kasparov at chess, which was one of those events that you typically see in a timeline of the evolution of technology. Back in those days, the new video game system was the Nintendo 64, and the internet was just introduced to instant messaging in the form of ICQ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, after being defeated by Deep Blue, Kasparov founded a new type of game. He called this “advanced chess,” also known as Centaur Chess. What was this? Well, for those that are unaware the Centaur is a mythological creature that had the upper body of a human being but had a lower body of a horse. In other words, half man, half horse. So what is Centaur Chess? Well, that’s where chess players competed against each other as half man, half computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.glassbeans.com/img/main/chess.jpg&#34; width=&#34;532&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, it’s a competition where teams would compete against each other in chess, but these teams could comprise of any combination of humans and computers. Teams can be fully comprised of chess masters, or IBM supercomputers, or some combination of the two (the Centaurs). In 2005, an advanced chess tournament was held, and the winners were a Centaur team of two relative amateurs named Steven Cramton and Zackary Stephen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their win was significant for several reasons. First of all, a good eight years after Kasparov’s famous defeat, a team comprised of both man and machine was able to defeat a team solely comprised of computers. In fact, my understanding is that Centaur teams still reign supreme over full computer teams even today (although I may be corrected on that, as coverage over chess seems to be hard to find these days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-yaml&#34;&gt;Man + machine &amp;gt; machine
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means that while computers might straight-up beat a person in a game of chess, there were still many aspects of human intelligence that machines could not replicate. Now, mind you, while this held true for relatively complicated games like chess, humans do not add anything to simpler games like checkers. What does this mean? The more complicated the game, the less likely you will be obsoleted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other significant aspect of Carmton and Stephen’s win was that as traditional chess players, they were relative amateurs. Their competition consisted of Centaur teams that were made up of one or more grandmasters. What this would seem to imply was that how good a team was in chess is not dependent on the quality of the chess player but in the player’s ability to utilize technology effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-yaml&#34;&gt;Skill in chess without computers ≠ skills in chess with computers 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why am I talking about chess? Well, there are a lot of things happening in the use of technology in the professional services industry (e.g. accounting, tax, consulting, and law). While the professional services industry has been changed by technology already, I don’t think we will be changed by technology as much in the last 20 years as we will be in the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My background is in consulting and accounting, so these are the areas that I know best. And if I stick with the parallels with chess, I believe the way my profession has utilized technology is more akin to everything that led up to Kasparov’s battle with Deep Blue. The chess world in the 90s started playing chess on computers rather than moving around wooden pieces on a physical board. This provided some advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was faster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could play with people quickly across long distances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your opponent was losing they couldn’t flip the board on you (though you might see this as a negative if you’re a board flipper yourself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the same with the accounting and consulting world. We moved our work onto computers. When I first entered the profession over ten years ago, I remember the big thing everything was touting was “the paperless office.” We now communicate with our clients and collaborate electronically. We also have the ability to process larger volumes of information much, much faster. So technology has had a significant impact on us, but it never fundamentally changed how we worked. What we did was move everything we did in the “old world” to an electronic one. So while we had to learn how to use some new tools, we didn’t have to relearn anything fundamental to the profession. Like chess, the moves and strategies we relied upon when playing on a wooden board still held true even when playing on a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When chess moved onto a computer, they changed how the game was played. When Kasparov founded Centaur chess, he changed the game. Strategies from traditional chess could in some cases be thrown out the window. And as Carmton and Stephen demonstrated in their 2005 championship, the best players are not necessarily going to be the ones that played the old game the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are at the forefront of a significant shift in our industry and profession. And this time it’s not just going to be a change in &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the game is played, but a fundamental shift in defining what the game is itself. Going forward, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to expand on these thoughts and hopefully push forward the industry as we collectively figure out what the new game will be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Eric Au</title>
      <link>http://www.glassbeans.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.glassbeans.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.glassbeans.com/img/main/profile.jpg&#34; width=&#34;132&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked in a client-facing role in the professional services industry for over ten years. Working at a professional services firm has provided me with some of the broadest work experiences available, starting with assurance/audit but quickly moving to leading teams in a wide range of consulting areas including valuations, risk management, and complex accounting litigation. During this time, the focus of my work was largely in forensic accounting and financial frauds. I currently lead research and culture in the area of data analytics for the Canadian arm of an international provider of accounting and other professional services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My formal education includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in mathematics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s degree in accounting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designation as a Canadian Chartered Accountant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designation as a Canadian Chartered Professional Accountant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designation as a Chartered Business Valuator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designation as a Certified Internal Auditor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been one of the most data-driven professional in practice. As such, nothing has excited me more than the business community’s willingness to embrace data and the more effective utilization of data to provide insights. In particular, the increased attention to data science and machine learning have allowed me to return to my roots, blending my domain knowledge in a broad range of consulting areas with my academic background in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is tremendous potential for the professional services industry and the accounting profession to take advantage of these advances. It will fundamentally change the way we work, and allow us to find new insights for our clients that were never before possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have accounting or financial data which you would like to explore, or if you are interested in working together to advance this field, I would love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>